A Guide to the Papers of Carter Glass 1858-1946, and n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Correspondence from residents of Bedford County (Box 84)
  A. Correspondence dealing with controversial issues of local interest; Questions, arguments, and petitions from citizens regarding the appointment of postmasters and changing rural routes, particularly in the communities of Huddleston and Abent; Replies to most of the letters; Requests for copies of certain bills, literature from the Agriculture Department, maps and other items.
- Correspondence: Lynchburg and Campbell County 1916, March-May (Box 85)
  A. Ca. 500 letters concerning state and local politics and appointments, requests for seeds and bulletins, newspaper business, legislation and personal matters.
- Correspondence 1915-1916 (Box 86)
  A. Letters from constituents concerning government jobs, requests for publications and seeds, financial reports and activities regarding his newspaper, etc.; Personal letters from Carter Glass' friends and children; Letter to E. F. Sheffey from Carter Glass in which Carter Glass gives his views of the way Bishop James Cannon handles is financial affairs.
- Correspondence, Roanoke City and County 1915 August-1916 February (Box 87)
  A. 500 letters concerning state and local politics, particularly appointment of postmaster, requests for seeds, bulletins, etc. and expressions of opinions on various legislation under consideration.
- Correspondence, including requests for Document 85 on liberalism testing 1928-1929 (Box 88)
  A. Letters requesting copies of Senate Document No. 85 or acknowledging receipt of the literature, concerning inspection procedures for determining whether cattle had contracted tuberculosis: Responses from Senators upon receipt of copies of Senate Document No. 85; Letters requesting copies of Senate Document No. 85, or entering similar complaints in connection with cattle inspectors.
  B. Copy of a bill introduced by Carter Glass on May 3, 1928, to allow cattle owners to be repaid for any losses suffered, as a result of the declaration of animals as tubercular.
- Correspondence from Roanoke City and County 1916 (Box 89)
  A. Letters concerning government jobs and appointments,; Requests for copies of bills and other literature; Requests for seeds; Queries regarding the effect of certain legislation on particular interests, etc.
- Correspondence from Montgomery County 1914 July-1916 January (Box 90)
  A. Miscellaneous correspondence with constituents in Montgomery County, Virginia: Suggestion from the postmaster at Radford, Virginia, that a campaign be organized to give Carter Glass a large vote in a forthcoming election, even though he would be unopposed; Request from an employee of a bank at Christiansburg, Virginia, that Carter Glass help him get a job at one of the Federal Reserve banks. Carter Glass answers that he does not make recommendations of this nature because of his intimate connection with the Federal Reserve System.
- Correspondence, Lynchburg and Campbell County 1916 May-August (Box 91)
  A. Letters regarding state and local political matters, including appointments, endorsements, etc.; Requests for seeds, bulletins and compensation; Letters to Walter Addison and M. Duerson concerning the News and Advance and other personal or business matters.
- Correspondence from residents of Floyd County (Box 92)
  A. Letters concerning postmastership, rural route changes and requests for seeds and government bulletins.
- Correspondence 1916-1917 (Box 93)
  A. About 600 letters concerning the local political situation, appointments, endorsements, requests for seeds, bulletins, etc. claims for compensation and various personal and business matters.
- Correspondence with constituents in Roanoke City and County 1916 May-November (Box 94)
  A. Miscellaneous correspondence with constituents during 1916: Editorial from the New York Sun, June 26, 1916, sent by a Roanoke, Virginia, insurance firm, backing the stand taken by Carter Glass in favor of branch banking; Several letters from real estate firms, opposing an amendment to the National Bank Act that would enable national banks to carry out certain insurance functions; Letter, September 8, 1916, from a Roanoke, Virginia, lawyer, congratulating Carter Glass on a speech distinguishing the Federal Reserve Act and the Aldrich bill; Letter from J. B. String fellow, a national bank examiner, thanking Carter Glass for aiding in the unsuccessful attempt to procure for him the job as Federal reserve agent at Richmond, Virginia.
- Correspondence with constituents in Floyd County 1916 December-1917 April (Box 95)
  A. Miscellaneous correspondence with constituents in Floyd County.
- Correspondence with constituents in Bedford County 1916 December-1917 April (Box 96)
  A. Miscellaneous correspondence with constituents from Bedford County.
- Speeches 1916-1928 (Box 97)
  A. Jefferson Day Dinner: Copies of speeches by Alfred E. Smith and Harry F. Byrd, among others, referring particularly to the proper relation of the government to the economy.
  B. Copy of a speech, "A Menacing Group Alliance," made in the Senate on March 23, 1922, by Carter Glass, refuting the statement that Woodrow Wilson agreed to the entry into World War I by the United States, because of the existence of certain secret treaties which were endangering the loans made by Morgan financial interests.
  D. Copy of a brief Armistice Day speech made by Carter Glass on November 11, 1923.
  E. Copies of a speech by Carter Glass in the Senate on June 14, 1929, relating the problems created by high protective tariffs to the agricultural interests.
  F. Copy of "The Truth about the War Department," a speech made by Carter Glass on February 7, 1918.
  G. Copies of a Jefferson Day speech by Carter Glass on April 13, 1916, explaining the need for banking reform and describing the remedies which has been prescribed for the financial difficulties.
  H. Copies of a speech, "Lest We Forget," by Carter Glass on February 16, 1923, concerning the advisability of accepting a proposal for lowering the debt of the British to the United States.
  I. Envelope supposed to contain a speech made by Carter Glass on June 14, 1917, in regard to an amendment to the Federal Reserve Act. The copy of the speech, however, is missing.
  J. Copy of a speech by Carter Glass on April 27, 1933, entitled "Shall We Go Over the Precipice?", opposing an amendment to the bill by which the country was to go off the old standard and also stating opposition to the bill. Carter Glass expresses the opinion that the bill would make the Federal Reserve System subservient to the Treasury Department.
  K. Copy of a speech made by Carter Glass at Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, on February 9, 1919, contrasting the banking system before the passing of the Federal Reserve Act, under which the failure of two New York banks caused a panic, with the banking community which survived a world war almost unscathed.
  L. Complimentary letters during the summer of 1936, on the speech by Carter Glass at a Democratic Convention, at which time he expressed dissatisfaction with the trend in national government.
  M. copy of a speech by Carter Glass in Chicago, Illinois, on March 21, 1919, in which he discusses liberty loans and the historical development of the Federal Reserve System.
  N. Statements, concerning Admiral Cary T. Grayson, which Carter Glass had printed in the Congressional Record.
  O. Statement placed in the Congressional Record on August 16, 1937, by Carter Glass, giving information about the activities of the Federal Deposit Insurance Company.
  P. Copies of a statement by Carter Glass, in connection with the victory liberty loan, entitled, "Business Need Not Fear Future."
  Q. Copies of a speech by Carter Glass in the House of Representatives on September 7, 1916, and a speech made during 1916 to the American Bankers' Association, dealing with the Federal Reserve Act, the reasons for its enactment, the process by which it became law, and the performance of the system.
  R. Copies of, "A Dangerous Nostrum," a speech by Carter Glass on June 22, 1926, opposing a bill designed to aid agricultural interests, because it was not in accordance with the fundamental principles of government.
- Speeches 1916-1928 (Box 98)
  A. Copies of a speech by Carter Glass on April 8, 1914, concerning the location of regional reserve banks with particular reference to placing a bank in Richmond, Virginia, rather than Baltimore, Maryland, Washington, D. C., or another city.
  B. Copy of speeches by Carter Glass on September 10 and 13, 1913, when he was trying to assure the passage by the House of Representatives of the bill, creating the Federal Reserve System.
  C. Copy of an address by Carter Glass during 1919 to the North Carolina Bankers Association, touching upon a wide range of subjects.
  D. Copy of a speech delivered on January 26, 1932, by Carter Glass, entitles, "Responsibility for Foreign Loans," and called by Carter Glass the "Turnip-head speech,"
  E. Copy of a speech by Carter Glass on June 9, 1925, before a meeting of the Robert Morris Associates.
  F. Copies of a speech made on March 20 in Minneapolis and March 21, 1919, in Chicago by Carter Glass, discussing the Federal Reserve System, the war, and the liberty loan campaign.
  G. Copies of booklet, "A Tale of Two Heifers," containing the statement of Carter Glass, opposing certain cattle inspection procedure being followed by employees of the State of Virginia.
  H. Copies of "Government by Investigation as. Government by Suppression," a speech made on April 15, 1924, by Carter Glass, suggesting that the Secretary of the Treasury permit an investigation of one of the Treasury agencies by a Senate Committee.
  I. Copy of a speech by Carter Glass on October 23, 1928, criticizing the actions of Herbert Hoover, when he served as Food Administrator in the World War I period, and refuting those who defended President Hoover.
  J. Copies of a speech, "The Facts About the Fiscal Policy of our Government During the Past Few Years," made by Carter Glass on November 1, 1932.
- Correspondence protesting Kitchen amendment to HR17606 1917 (Box 99)
  A. Copies of amendments to the Federal Reserve Act, submitted on April 27, 1917, by the Banking and Currency Committee, of which Carter Glass was chairman, for consideration on the House floor; Copy of a letter of May 16, 1917, from William G. McAdoo, Secretary of the Treasury, to President Wilson, giving his views on the situation with respect to several amendments to the Federal Reserve Act, then ready for resolution in conference committee. William G. McAdoo mentions bringing Carter Glass around to accepting the issuance of Federal Reserve notes against gold and expresses opposition to granting permission for certain banks to make exchange charges; Letter of October 2, 1916, from Paul M. Warburg of the Federal Reserve Board, covering a variety of points, considered of importance at the time, such as stressing the adequacy of gold balances held by member banks; Letter, Carter Glass to James B. Forgan, January 15, 1917, in which Carter Glass inquires about the justification for the position, taken by bankers who had previously considered the Federal Reserve Act an inflationary measure, that Federal Reserve notes should be used as reserves; Telegram, November 11, 1916, from Bernard M. Baruch; Letter from W. P. G. Harding, governor of the Federal Reserve Board, January 22, 1917, announcing withdrawal of a recommendation that Federal Reserve notes be issued against gold certificates; Letter from Paul M. Warburg, of the Board of Governors, January 30, 1917, asking that Carter Glass try to get Congress to reconsider the section of the Federal Reserve Act, relating bank loans to directors; Letters to and from Carter Glass concerning private bankers as directors of national banks, the performance of insurance services by small national banks, and the check collection amendment offered in 1917 by Representative Kitchen and by Senator Hardwick; Letter from Carter Glass to W. P. G. Harding at the Federal Reserve Board, stating that a return to the former system of check collection would be undesirable; Several letters from bakers favoring the Kitchen bill; Correspondence with John V. Farwell about the Kitchen bill; Letter from Representative Edmund Platt, favoring the exacting of exchange charges; Reply of Carter Glass to the letter from Edmund Platt; Numerous letters from merchants, both retail and wholesale, throughout the country, protesting the charging of exchange during the check clearance process. For example, there are letters from grocers, drygoods concerns, and hardware stores; Letter from W. P. G. Harding, Governor of the Federal Reserve Board, accompanying a statement of the effect of a proposed amendment to the reserve requirements; Letter, April 30, 1917, from Paul M. Warburg, of the Federal Reserve Board, noting an enclosure felt to be of interest to Carter Glass; Letters sent to the Board of Governors, opposing the Kitchen amendment concerning exchange charges, and transmitted by Warren G. Harding to Carter Glass; Correspondence of the Comptroller of the Currency, relating to exchange charges on checks, including letters from John Skelton Williams to Carter Glass.
- Correspondence with the Army Department 1917 (Box 100)
  A. Correspondence in connection with military service problems brought to the attention of Carter Glass by constituents.
- Correspondence (Box 101)
  A. Carter Glass to Penrose regarding Hudson matter, 9 October 1919, an extension of interest payments on loans to European borrowers; Russell C. Leffingwell to Carter Glass, 30 January 1936, regarding subrogation of collateral for war loan; Russell C. Leffingwell to Carter Glass, 5 January 1936; Mellon to Carter Glass regarding cables sent by Carter Glass; Houston to Carter Glass regarding cables; Leffingwell to Carter Glass, 19 December 1922. Memo regarding the legality of foreign loans, 17 December 1922; Memo of Treasury, 3 March 1921, regarding foreign loans; Memo, 2 August 1921, to Carter Glass regarding refunding of foreign obligations; Memo for secretary, 25 October 1919, regarding money market; Memo to Carter Glass from (?) Kelley regarding foreign loans, 3 March 1921; Russell C. Leffingwell to Carter Glass, 15 December 1920, regarding reversal of War Finance Corporation; Russell C. Leffingwell to Kellogg regarding the reserve (A good memo); Leffingwell to (?) versus soldier's bonus; Leffingwell address before the Academy, 12 May 1922; Leffingwell's address before Political Science Association, 30 April 1922; Carter Glass to Norman H. Davis regarding French finance; Carter Glass to the President, 28 May 1918 [1919], regarding the removal of embargoes on coin, bullion and currency by Presidential proclamation; President from Carter Glass, 2 June 1911, regarding forging of notes; Carter Glass to President regarding appointment of John Skelton Williams, 24 January 1919.
- Correspondence protesting the Hardwick amendment to H. R. 3613 1917 (Box 102)
  A. Numerous letters opposing the Hardwick amendment which would renew the right of the banks to levy exchange charges on checks.
  B. Pamphlets explaining the Hardwick amendment and discussing the collection policies of the Federal Reserve System.
  C. Notes from several Senators, stating opposition to the Hardwick amendment and expressing the hope that the Conference Committee would refuse to accept this portion of the bill.
  D. Letter from an organ of the American Bankers Association in favor of the Hardwick amendment.
  E. Copy of a telegram from Carter Glass to William G. McAdoo, Secretary of the Treasury, concerning possibility of urging the President to veto the bill, if the Hardwick amendment is accepted by the Conference Committee.
  F. Letter from Paul M. Warburg on April 28, 1917, sending a statement to Carter Glass, intended to keep him informed about the attitude of influential persons toward exchange charges.
  G. Note from W. P. G. Harding, Governor of the Federal Reserve Board, on December 4, 1916, enclosing a substitute amendment to that part of the Federal Reserve Act dealing with membership requirements, suggested by H. Parker Willis.
  H. Letter from W. P. G. Harding, Governor of the Federal Reserve Board, sending correspondence about the Kitchen bill to Carter Glass.
  I. Letter, Carter Glass to Representative C. A. Brand, expressing the hope that the President would veto the bill containing the Hardwick amendment.
  J. Letter from the president of the Girard National Bank favoring the charging of exchange by banks.
  K. Telegram, Benjamin Strong to Carter Glass, of the New York Federal Reserve Bank, opposing the plan to permit the charging of exchange.
  L. Letter from John Perrin, of the Federal Reserve Bank of San Francisco, concerning the responsibilities of the Federal Reserve Agent.
  M. Copy of the Federal Reserve Act as amended to September 7, 1916, and a copy of the Kitchen bill.
  N. Copies of a report by the Federal Reserve Bank of New York on the check collection system, prepared by Pierre Jay.
  O. Copies of the pamphlet, entitled, "The Collection System of the Federal Reserve Banks."
  P. Copies of a ten-page paper on "A Dispassionate Analysis of the Subject of 'Exchange' on Checks, Being a Collection Fee Assessed by City Banks when Paying checks Drawn Against Banks in Other Cities, or in Towns and Villages."
- Correspondence protesting Hardwick amendment on H. R. 3673 (Box 103)
  A. Telegram from Carter Glass, May 16, 1917, to, George A. Knapp, J. H. McLaurin, and several retailers and wholesalers, suggesting that provisions with regard to check collections, contained in a bill before a Conference Committee, be opposed by business interests.
  B. Letters and telegrams opposing the Hardwick amendment, permitting banks to make exchange charges for handling checks: Telegram from William G. McAdoo; Letter from J. H. Tregoe, Secretary of the National Association of Credit Men, showing how the group was cooperating in opposing the Hardwick amendment; Correspondence with Thomas A. Fernley, Secretary of the National Wholesale Dry Goods Association, who did much of the work involved in flooding Congress men with messages opposing a return to former exchange charge practices; Letters from numerous Congress men, promising to give thorough consideration to the problem of exchange charges; Correspondence from Frederick A. Delano, of the Federal Reserve Board, concerning the check clearance provisions of the Federal Reserve Act; Memorandum from the Federal Reserve Board, concerning statements made by J. F. Thralls; Letters from John Skelton Williams, Comptroller of the Currency, opposing the Hardwick amendment.
  C. Letters from banks supporting the return of the privilege of making exchange charges.
  D. Letter from John Skelton Williams, Comptroller of the Currency, accompanying a report on usury charges.
  E. Paper on, "Domestic Exchange," by Robert D. Kent, president of a bank in Passaic, New Jersey.
  F. Letter from W. P. G. Harding, Governor of the Federal Reserve Board, stating that the acceptance of the bill containing the Hardwick amendment would cost the government large sums of money in connection with Liberty Loan subscriptions.
  G. Telegram from William G. McAdoo, secretary of the Treasury, expressing the hope that action on amendments to the Federal Reserve Act would result favorably for purposes of governmental borrowing.
  H. Copy of the Journal of the American Bankers Association, May, 1917, containing a review of the proposed amendments to the Federal Reserve Act.
  I. Copy of the Federal Reserve Bulletin, February, 1917, containing explanations of the proposed amendments to the Federal Reserve Act.
  J. Copy of a proposed amendment to several sections of the Federal Reserve Act, introduced in the Senate on May 9, 1917.
  K. Copy of the Federal Reserve Act as amended up to September 7, 1916.
  L. Letter from Paul M. Warburg, of the Federal Reserve Board, discussing the anticipated effects of impending payments for Liberty Loans bonds upon the Federal Reserve banks and stressing the need for increasing reserve requirements, as would result from the proposed amendments to the Federal Reserve Act.
  M. Balance sheet, prepared by the Comptroller of the Currency, showing the condition of the national banks.
  N. Statistics showing the number of various types of business concerns in the United States.
  O. Letters purporting in many cases to be describing the poor operation of the existing system of check collection, including letters from bankers transmitted by the Federal Reserve Board and letters from business concerns sent by the Comptroller of the Currency.
  P. Statements of Federal Reserve officials and the Comptroller of the Currency, concerning the effect of exchange charges on the banks and the attitude of bankers in 1916 toward the check collection system.
- Correspondence (Box 104)
  A. Several letters of protest against the Hardwick amendment; Several letters in favor of reinstatement of the Hardwick amendment; Letter to Carter Glass if favor of establishment of a foreign exchange bureau in the Federal Reserve System; Carter Glass to McLane Tilton regarding Kitchen amendments; Fitz Henry to Carter Glass regarding insurance of deposits for non-member banks, 23 March 1918; Carter Glass to Scheffy regarding Hardwick amendment; Carter Glass to George Moore regarding Hardwick amendment; Sabath to Carter Glass regarding Hardwick amendment; Carter Glass to Tregoe regarding Hardwick amendment; Carter Glass to Campbell regarding Hardwick amendment; Carter Glass also opposed Kitchen amendment in the House version of the Hardwick amendment in the Senate; George Seay to Carter Glass regarding Kitchen amendment; Pierre Jay to Carter Glass regarding the advertising of the Federal Reserve System; Letter from various sources protesting the high cost of living and demands for relief pouring in first half of 1917; Analysis of a bill to coordinate, unify and consolidate the financial system of the United States, 6 January 1917; Carter Glass to Joseph P. Tumulty regarding the help of the National Association of Credit Men, 20 June 1917; Carter Glass to Fernley, 20 January 1917, regarding Hardwick amendment; Carter Glass to Aiken of the Federal Reserve Bank of Boston on amendment to the Federal Reserve Act; Pierre Jay to Carter Glass regarding par collection fight; Peron to Carter Glass regarding par collection fight; Orr of National Association of Credit Men to pressure senators on Hardwick Bill; Carter Glass to C. L. Cobb; Carter Glass to Burton, 27 September 1917, regarding collateral for Federal Reserve notes; E. P. Miller of Lynchburg, to Carter Glass regarding the need for $1.00 bills; Carter Glass to Congressman Cornhill regarding the keeping of government securities at par.
- Correspondence on personal and legislative matters 1925-1930 (Box 105)
  A. Walter Wyatt, General Counsel for the Federal Reserve Board: Letters and data concerning the legal aspects of the par clearance of checks.